Williams Obstetrics.
Chapter 8: Teratology, Teratogens, and Fetotoxic.
Agents Teratology.
Criteria For Determining Teratogenicity.
Studies In Pregnant Women.
Counseling For Medication Exposure.
Labeling Requirements.
Teratogenic And Fetotoxic Agents.
Drugs Of Abuse.
References.
Birth defects are common.
Of all newborns, 2 to 3 percent have a major congenital abnormality detectable at birth (Cragan, 2009; Dolk, 2010).
Some medications undoubtedly pose significant risk to the developing embryo or fetus .
However, 80 percent of birth defects do not have an obvious etiology, and of those with an identified cause, nearly 95 percent of cases have chromosomal or genetic origins .
The U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) (2018) estimates that <1 percent of all birth defects are caused by medications .
Table 8-1.
Selected Teratogenic and Fetotoxic Agents Figure 8-1.
Etiology of birth defects.
Known and unknown causes of 5504 birth defects from a population-based review of 270,878 births.
That said, significant concern surrounds medication use in pregnancy.
This is because many pregnant women are prescribed medications and because safety data are often lacking.
Investigators from the National Birth Defects Prevention Study found that women take an average of two to three medications per pregnancy and that 70 percent use medication in the first trimester .
A population-based review from Canada found that 65 percent of women fill ≥1 prescription during pregnancy .
Between 2010 and 2019, the FDA approved 290 new drugs, and only 11 percent had human data related to pregnancy .
Teratology.
The study of birth defects and their etiology is termed teratology, derived from the Greek teratos, meaning monster.
A teratogen may be broadly defined as any agent that acts during embryonic or fetal development to produce a permanent alteration of form or function.
Thus, a teratogen may be a medication or other chemical substance, a physical or environmental factor such as heat or radiation, a maternal metabolite as in diabetes or phenylketonuria, or an infection such as cytomegalovirus.
Strictly defined, a teratogen causes structural abnormalities.
A hadegen —after the god Hades—is an agent that interferes with normal maturation and function of an organ.
A trophogen is an agent that alters growth.
Substances in the latter two groups typically affect development in the fetal period or postnatally and are thus fetotoxins rather than teratogens.
# Criteria for Determining Teratogenicity.
The guidelines shown in Table 8-2 were proposed by Shepard (1994) as a framework for discussion and have proved useful for nearly 30 years.
Although each individual criterion is not required to establish teratogenicity, the following tenets should be considered : Table 8-2.
Criteria for Determining Teratogenicity • The abnormality has been completely characterized.
This is preferably done by a geneticist or dysmorphologist because different genetic and environmental factors may produce similar defects.
It is easiest to prove causation when a rare exposure produces a rare anomaly, when at least three cases with the same exposure have been identified, and when the defect is severe.
The agent must cross the placenta.
Although almost all drugs cross the placenta, transport must be of sufficient quantity to directly influence embryonic or fetal development or to alter maternal or placental metabolism to exert an indirect effect.
Placental transfer depends on maternal metabolism; on specific characteristics of the drug, such as protein binding and storage, molecular size, electrical charge, and lipid solubility; and on placental metabolism, such as by the cytochrome P450 enzyme system.
In early pregnancy, the placenta also has a relatively thick membrane that slows diffusion.
Exposure must occur during a critical developmental period.
The preimplantation period is the 2 weeks between fertilization and implantation and is known as the “all or none” period.
As the zygote undergoes cleavage, an insult damaging a large number of cells typically
causes embryonic death.
However, if only a few cells are injured, compensation may be possible and allow normal development.
The embryonic period extends from the second through the eighth week postconception.
It encompasses organogenesis and is thus the most crucial period with regard to structural malformations.
Critical developmental periods for each organ system are illustrated in Figure 7-2 (p. 122).
The fetal period, which is beyond 8 weeks postconception, is characterized by continued maturation and functional development.
During this time, certain organs remain vulnerable.
A biologically plausible association is supportive.
Because birth defects and medication exposures are both common, they may be temporally but not causally related.
Epidemiological findings must be consistent.
Because initial evaluation of teratogen exposure is often retrospective, it may be hampered by recall bias, inadequate reporting, and incomplete assessment of the exposed population.
Potential confounding factors include varying dosages, concomitant drug therapy, and comorbid maternal disease(s).
Familial and environmental variables also can influence development of birth defects.
Thus, an important criterion for teratogenicity is that two or more highquality epidemiological studies report similar findings.
Last, a relative risk of 3.0 or greater is generally considered necessary to support the hypothesis, whereas a lesser risk is interpreted with caution .
The suspected teratogen causes a defect in animal studies.
This criterion is not obligatory, and for litigation purposes, establishment of a causal relationship between an exposure and an outcome in humans requires human data .
Failure to employ these tenets and criteria has contributed to erroneous conclusions regarding the safety of some widely used drugs.
The poster child for this is the medicolegal fiasco surrounding Bendectin.
This antiemetic was a combination of doxylamine and pyridoxine, with or without dicyclomine.
More than 30 million women used this drug worldwide, and it was safe and effective for nausea and vomiting in early pregnancy.
The 3-percent congenital anomaly rate among exposed fetuses was not different from the background rate .
Despite considerable evidence that this combination of an antihistamine and a B-vitamin is not teratogenic, Bendectin was the target of numerous lawsuits, and the financial burden of defending these forced its withdrawal from the marketplace in 1983.
Consequently, hospitalization rates for hyperemesis doubled .
Ironically, the combination of doxylamine and pyridoxine was subsequently remarketed under the brand name Diclegis and was approved by the FDA in 2013.
# Studies in Pregnant Women.
The study of medication safety—or teratogenicity—in pregnant women is fraught with complications.
First, animal studies are necessary but insufficient.
For example, thalidomide was considered harmless in several animal species but resulted in phocomelia in thousands of children born across Europe in the late 1950s and early 1960s.
Second, medications are rarely approved by the FDA for a pregnancy-related indication.
Despite the Common Rule’s removal of pregnant women as a vulnerable population, pregnant women are routinely excluded from research (Health and Human Services, 2017; Spong, 2018).
Last, drug concentration and thus embryo-fetal exposure are affected by pregnancy physiology.
This includes changes in volume of distribution, cardiac output, gastrointestinal absorption, hepatic metabolism, and renal clearance.
In the absence of research trials, counseling is based on case reports or series, case-control studies, cohort studies, and pregnancy registry data.
Case Reports and Series Many major teratogens were first described by clinicians who observed a rare defect occurring after a rare exposure.
This has been termed the “astute clinician model” .
Congenital rubella syndrome was identified in this way by Gregg (1941), an Australian ophthalmologist whose observations challenged the view that the uterine environment was
impervious to noxious agents.
Other teratogens identified through case series include thalidomide and alcohol (Jones, 1973; Lenz, 1962).
Shepard (2002a) recommended that establishment of teratogenicity in this way requires proven exposure at a critical time in development and at least three such cases.
Unfortunately, teratogens are less likely to be identified if the exposure is uncommon, if the defects are relatively nonspecific, or if abnormalities develop in only a small proportion of exposed fetuses.
A major limitation of case series is their lack of a control group.
Case-control Studies These studies begin with groups of affected infants (cases) and unaffected controls and are structured to allow retrospective assessment of prenatal exposure to particular substances.
Case-control studies are an efficient way to study rare outcomes .
These permit investigators to evaluate associations and generate useful hypotheses.
However, case-control studies have inherent potential for recall bias.
Namely, parents of an affected infant are often more likely to recall exposure than those whose child is not ill.
Confounding by indication is another concern, that is, the indication for the medication may be the cause of the birth defect.
And importantly, birth defect registries have statistical power to detect small differences that may not be clinically meaningful.
Grimes and Schulz (2012) have cautioned that unless odds ratios in case-control studies are above three- to fourfold, the observed associations may not be correct.
The National Birth Defects Prevention Study.
Funded by Congress and coordinated by the National Center on Birth Defects and Developmental Disabilities, the National Birth Defects Prevention Study (NBDPS) took place between 1997 and 2013 across ten states with active birth defects surveillance programs.
It is an excellent example of a population-based casecontrol study.
The study involved approximately 32,000 cases and nearly 12,000 controls.
Live births, stillbirths, and terminated pregnancies were included.
Clinical geneticists reviewed each potential case, and standardized telephone interviews were conducted with women whose pregnancies were affected or unaffected to obtain information regarding medication exposure and risk factors (Mitchell, 2011; Reefhuis, 2015).
The NBDPS identified novel—although often small—associations between individual birth defects and several classes of medications.
These include antibiotics, antidepressants, antiemetics, antihypertensives, asthma medications, nonsteroidal antiinflammatory drugs (NSAIDs), and opioids (Ailes, 2016; Broussard, 2011; Fisher, 2018; Hernandez, 2012; Lin, 2012; Munsie, 2011).
Pregestational diabetes was significantly associated with 46 of 50 different abnormalities studied .
The NBDPS also found associations between birth defects and exposures such as secondhand smoke, pesticides, and nitrogen oxide, which is a marker of traffic-related air pollution (Hoyt, 2016; Rocheleau, 2015; Stingone, 2017).
The NBDPS had several key limitations related to study design.
First, interviews were conducted 6 weeks to 2 years following delivery, which raised the likelihood of recall bias.
For example, 25 percent of women could not remember which antibiotic they had taken .
Additionally, only two thirds of women agreed to participate, and there were differences in ethnicity and socioeconomic status between cases and controls.
These factors may have contributed to selection bias .
Further, medical records were not reviewed to verify dosage, and this precluded assessment of dose-response relationships.
Last, a major limitation was that because the NBDPS included only a small number of cases of each birth defect and analyzed them for many different maternal exposures, it was not possible to adjust for multiple comparisons.
As a result, some of the observed associations were likely due to chance .
As one example, the study of antibiotics and birth defects included 43 comparisons and identified four significant associations, but chance alone predicted that two
associations would be identified .
Importantly, the NBDPS was able to identify statistically significant odds ratios for which the absolute risk was quite low.
Such findings have the potential to complicate counseling and prenatal management.
In many instances, the risk identified by the NBDPS was as low as 1 case per 1000 exposed pregnancies.
Cohort Studies These studies begin with cohorts of pregnant women who are exposed or unexposed to a particular medication.
The percentage of infants or children affected with birth defects is examined in each cohort.
Because individual birth defects are rare, cohort studies require a very large sample size.
Medicaid datasets and private insurance claims databases are commonly used for cohort studies of teratogenicity in the United States .
Inability to adjust for confounding variables—such as the indication for which the medication was needed—is an important limitation of this study design.
Pregnancy Registries Potentially harmful agents may be monitored by clinicians who prospectively enroll exposed pregnancies in a registry.
The FDA (2021) maintains an active webpage of Pregnancy Exposure Registries.
As of 2021, this included registries for 115 individual medications and for medication groups used to treat asthma, attention deficit hyperactivity disorder, autoimmune diseases, cancer, diabetes, epilepsy, hepatitis B and C, human immunodeficiency virus infection, hypercholesterolemia, inborn errors of metabolism, inflammatory bowel disease, multiple sclerosis, narcolepsy, psychiatric illness, and transplant rejection.
Similar to case series, exposure registries are hampered by lack of a control group.
The prevalence of an abnormality identified through a registry requires knowledge of the baseline prevalence of that anomaly in the population.
Investigators typically use a birth defect registry to assess population prevalence.
One example is the Metropolitan Atlanta Congenital Defects Program, which is an active surveillance program established in 1967 for fetuses and infants with birth defects.
Counseling For Medication Exposure.
Questions regarding medication and illicit drug use should be part of routine preconceptional and prenatal care.
Misinformation is common.
Individuals tend to underestimate the background risk for birth defects in the general population and exaggerate potential risks associated with medication exposure.
In one population-based study of more than 270,000 births from Utah that included 5500 fetuses and infants with major birth defects, only 4 cases were attributed to medication exposure (see Fig. 8-1) .
And yet, Koren and colleagues (1989) reported that a fourth of women exposed to nonteratogenic drugs thought they had a 25-percent risk for fetal anomalies.
Misinformation may be amplified by inaccurate reports in the lay press.
Knowledgeable counseling may allay anxiety considerably and may even avert pregnancy termination.
Several sources are available to assist providers with accurate and updated risk information.
With recent changes to the FDA labeling requirements, discussed next, the manufacturer’s prescribing information has become increasingly helpful.
We recommend using this content for initial counseling.
Published research studies can be identified using PubMed, a free database tool from the National Center for Biomedical Information.
Additionally, online databases such as Reprotox, TERIS, and Shepard’s Online Catalog of Teratogenic Agents offer detailed reviews of medication risks.
Lactmed, a database from the National Library of Medicine, specifically deals with medication use by breastfeeding women.
Its entries on specific medications describe levels in breast milk and potential effects on the infant.
Ultimately, it is the responsibility of the clinician to interpret risk information.
Medication dosage and route, timing of exposure during pregnancy, other medications used, and underlying medical condition(s) are considered in this analysis.
Last, the risk from lack of treatment also is weighed.
# Labeling Requirements.
In 1979, the FDA
developed a letter classification system (A, B, C, D, X) to provide therapeutic guidance for prescribing medications in pregnancy.
These letter categories were intended to simplify risk-benefit data using summary statements regarding available evidence from human or animal studies of embryonic–fetal risk.
Unfortunately, information regarding medication risk was often incomplete and led to an overreliance on the category definition.
To address these deficiencies, new FDA (2014, 2020b) labeling requirements were created and went into effect in 2015.
The label provides a framework to aid prescribing decisions by more clearly communicating risks and benefits.
Information about each medication now incorporates a detailed summary of risks, clinical considerations, and available data .
Registry information is included when available.
For each medication, a lactation subsection is provided, and a section addressing potential risks in females and males of reproductive potential is presented.
In addition to risks associated with specific medications, the label is required to include the background risk of major birth defects and miscarriage in the general population.
Because of the level of detail in the new labels, the information can be indispensable for counseling.
Table 8-3.
Food and Drug Administration Pregnancy Labeling Requirements # Presenting Risk Information.
Counseling should cover not only the embryonic and fetal risks from drug exposure, but also the risks and/or genetic implications of the condition for which the drug is administered.
Risks associated with not treating the condition also are described.
Even the manner in which information is presented affects perception.
For example, women given negative information—such as a 2-percent chance of a malformed newborn—are more likely to perceive an exaggerated risk than women given positive information —such as a 98-percent chance of an unaffected infant .
Instead of citing a higher odds ratio, it may be helpful to provide the absolute risk for a particular defect or the attributable risk, which is the difference between prevalence in exposed and unexposed individuals .
The association between oral corticosteroid medications and cleft lip sounds far more concerning when presented as a tripling or 200-percent increase in risk than when described as an increase from 1 to 3 cases per 1000 or as a 99.7-percent likelihood of no cleft development following exposure.
With a few notable exceptions, most commonly prescribed drugs and medications can be used with relative safety during pregnancy.
Many drugs discussed in this chapter are low-risk teratogens, which are medications that produce defects in fewer than 10 per 1000 maternal exposures .
Because risks conferred by low-risk teratogens are so close to the population background rate of fetal anomalies, they may not be a major factor in deciding whether to discontinue treatment for an important condition .
All women have an approximate 3-percent chance of having a fetus or newborn with a major anomaly.
Although exposure to a confirmed teratogen may elevate this risk, the magnitude of the increase is usually only 1 or 2 percent or at most, doubled or tripled.
The concept of risk versus benefit is often central to counseling.
Some untreated diseases pose a more serious threat to both mother and fetus than medication exposure risks.
Teratogenic And Fetotoxic Agents.
Considering the thousands of compounds available, relatively few medications and other substances are considered to be major human teratogens or to have significant fetotoxicity.
The most common examples are listed in Table 8-1.
With few exceptions, in every clinical situation potentially requiring therapy with a known teratogen, alternative drugs can be given with relative safety.
Realizing limitations in available evidence, pregnant women should be advised to take any medication only when it is clearly needed.
Detailed sonography is generally indicated if the fetus has been exposed to any major teratogen during the embryonic period.
# Alcohol.
Ethanol is
a potent and prevalent teratogen.
It is considered the leading cause of preventable developmental disabilities worldwide .
In the United States, alcohol use is reported by 10 percent of pregnant women .
Nearly 10 percent of such women admit to binge drinking in the first trimester, and 1 percent report binge drinking in the second and third trimesters.
The fetal effects of alcohol abuse have been recognized since the 1800s.
Lemoine (1968) and Jones (1973) and their coworkers are credited with describing the spectrum of alcohol-related fetal defects known as fetal alcohol syndrome.
Criteria are shown in Table 8-4 .
For every child with the syndrome, many more are born with neurobehavioral deficits from alcohol exposure.
Fetal alcohol spectrum disorder (FASD) is an umbrella term that includes five conditions attributed to prenatal alcohol damage: (1) fetal alcohol syndrome, (2) partial fetal alcohol syndrome, (3) alcohol-related birth defects, (4) alcohol-related neurodevelopmental disorder, and (5) neurobehavioral disorder associated with prenatal alcohol exposure .
The prevalence of FASD exceeds 1 percent in 76 countries, and 1 in 13 women who consume alcohol in pregnancy has a child with FASD .
The birth prevalence of fetal alcohol syndrome is estimated to be as high as 1 percent in the United States (Centers for Disease Control, 2015; Guerri, 2009).
Further, studies of school-aged children have identified FASD in 2 to 5 percent (May, 2009, 2014).
Table 8-4.
Criteria for Prenatal Alcohol Exposure, Fetal Alcohol Syndrome, and Alcohol-Related Birth Defects Criteria Fetal alcohol syndrome has specific criteria .
These include central nervous system (CNS) abnormalities, pre- or postnatal growth impairment, and a characteristic pattern of minor facial abnormalities .
Similar criteria have been established for the other conditions that make up FASD .
Prenatal alcohol exposure criteria also are available to assist with assessment.
Figure 8-2.
Fetal alcohol syndrome.
A. At 2½ years.
B. At 12 years.
Note persistence of short palpebral fissures, epicanthal folds, flat midface, hypoplastic philtrum, and thin upper vermilion border.
Reproduced with permission from Streissguth AP, Clarren, SK, Jones KL.
Natural history of fetal alcohol syndrome: a 10-year follow-up of eleven patients, Lancet.
1985 Jul 13;2(8446):85–91.
Alcohol-related birth defects include cardiac and renal anomalies, orthopedic problems, and abnormalities of the eyes and ears .
An association has further been reported between periconceptional alcohol use and omphalocele and gastroschisis .
There are no established sonographic criteria for prenatal diagnosis of fetal alcohol syndrome.
At Parkland Hospital, we reserve detailed sonography for pregnancies that have met the exposure criteria listed in Table 8-4.
Thirdtrimester assessment of fetal growth also should be considered.
Fetal vulnerability to alcohol is modified by genetic and environmental factors, nutritional status, coexisting maternal disease, and maternal age .
Binge drinking, however, is believed to pose particularly high risk for alcohol-related birth defects and has also been linked to a greater risk for stillbirth (Centers for Disease Control, 2015; Strandberg-Larsen, 2008).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), and the American Academy of Pediatrics have stressed that no amount of alcohol can be considered safe in pregnancy (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020a; Williams, 2015).
# Antiepileptic Medications.
Traditionally, women with epilepsy requiring treatment with medication were informed that their risk for fetal malformations was increased.
More recent data suggest that the risk may not be as great as once thought, particularly for newer agents.
The most frequently reported anomalies are orofacial clefts, cardiac malformations, and neural-tube defects.
Of agents in current use, valproic acid confers the highest risk .
The North American Antiepileptic Drug (NAAED) Pregnancy Registry reported that
major malformations developed in 9 percent of fetuses with first-trimester valproate exposure.
This included a 4-percent risk for neural-tube defects .
School-aged children with prior in utero exposure to valproic acid have poorer cognitive development —including significantly lower intelligence quotient (IQ) scores—than children exposed to other antiepileptic drugs (Bromley, 2014; Meador, 2009).
Regarding other specific anticonvulsants, one metaanalysis identified increased malformation rates among exposed children compared with rates among children born to women with untreated epilepsy.
Rates were twofold higher among children exposed to carbamazepine or phenytoin, threefold higher among those exposed to phenobarbital, and fourfold higher among those exposed to topiramate as monotherapy .
The risk for fetal malformations is approximately doubled if multiple agents are required .
Several older anticonvulsants may produce a constellation of findings similar to the fetal hydantoin syndrome.
The syndrome is characterized by distinctive features such as hypertelorism, low nasal bridge, and midface hypoplasia; hypoplasia of the distal phalanges and nails; growth impairment; and intellectual disability.
Importantly, evidence to date suggests that these risks do not appear to hold for the newer agents levetiracetam and lamotrigine (Mølgaard-Nielsen, 2011; Weston, 2016).
A review of 208 pregnancies with first-trimester lamotrigine exposure from the Israeli Teratology Information Service found no increase in the rate of major malformations and no case of oral cleft .
Similarly, the International Lamotrigine Pregnancy Registry followed more than 1500 pregnancies with first trimester exposure and observed no effect on the rate of major malformations .
The Motherisk Program reviewed eight studies of levetiracetam and concluded that monotherapy was associated with a 2-percent major malformation rate, no different from that for the general population .
More recently, a review of 465 pregnancies reported to the Levetiracetam Pregnancy Registry found no evidence of teratogenicity .
Providers are encouraged to enroll pregnant women treated with antiepileptic medication in the NAAED Pregnancy Registry.
Management of epilepsy in pregnancy is discussed in Chapter 63 (p. 1128).
# Angiotensin-converting Enzyme Inhibitors and Receptor.
Blocking Drugs These medications may result in angiotensin-converting enzyme (ACE)inhibitor fetopathy.
Normal renal development depends on the fetal reninangiotensin system.
ACE-inhibitor medication may cause fetal hypotension and renal hypoperfusion, with subsequent ischemia and anuria (Guron, 2000; Pryde, 1993).
Reduced perfusion can result in fetal-growth restriction and calvarium maldevelopment, and oligohydramnios may lead to pulmonary hypoplasia and limb contractures .
Because angiotensin-receptor blockers have a similar mechanism of action, concerns regarding fetotoxicity have been generalized to include this entire medication class.
A recent review of nearly 200 pregnancies from teratology information services found a 30-percent fetopathy risk with angiotensin-receptor blockers compared with a 3-percent risk with ACE-inhibitor exposure beyond 20 weeks’ gestation .
Concerns about ACE-inhibitor embryotoxicity have largely been disproven.
In 2006, a review of 29,000 infants from the Tennessee Medicaid database identified a two- to threefold greater risk for neonatal cardiac and CNS abnormalities among the 209 that had prenatal ACE-inhibitor exposure .
Subsequent larger studies have not corroborated these observations.
In a retrospective cohort study of more than 460,000 pregnancies, risks for birth defects were not higher with ACE inhibitors than with other antihypertensive medications .
Similarly, a review of 1.3 million pregnancies from the Medicaid Analytic eXtract found no increased risk for any malformation with ACE-inhibitor exposure after adjusting for confounding factors such as diabetes .
Thus, women with inadvertent first-trimester exposure to these medications may be reassured.
Importantly, given the many therapeutic options for treating hypertension during pregnancy, discussed in Chapter 53 (p. 949), ACE inhibitors and angiotensin receptor-blocking drugs should be avoided in pregnancy.
# Antifungal Medications.
From this class of drugs, fluconazole has been associated with a pattern of congenital malformations resembling the autosomal recessive Antley-Bixler syndrome.
Abnormalities include oral clefts, abnormal facies, and cardiac, skull, long-bone, and joint abnormalities.
Such findings have been reported only with chronic, first-trimester, high-dose treatment at doses of 400 to 800 mg daily.
Regarding low-dose treatment of vulvovaginal candidiasis, the Motherisk Program conducted a systematic review of pregnancies with first-trimester oral fluconazole exposure of 150 or 300 mg in total .
The overall risk for birth defects was not greater, although a small increase in rates of cardiac malformations could not be excluded.
A population-based cohort study from Denmark identified a threefold greater risk for tetralogy of Fallot following exposure to low-dose fluconazole (Mølgaard-Nielsen, 2013).
The birth prevalence of tetralogy of Fallot rose from 3 to 10 cases per 10,000.
Notably, investigators did not identify increased risks for 14 other birth defects previously associated with exposure to high-dose azole antifungal agents (Mølgaard-Nielsen, 2013).
A subsequent review of more than 37,000 pregnancies with first-trimester fluconazole exposure did not identify an association with cardiac abnormalities .
Based on reported risks, we do not perform detailed sonography or fetal echocardiography following low-dose fluconazole exposure.
# Antiinflammatory Agents.
Nonsteroidal Antiinflammatory Drugs This drug class includes both aspirin and traditional NSAIDs such as ibuprofen and indomethacin.
They exert their effects by inhibiting prostaglandin synthesis.
In a report from the NBDPS, at least 20 percent of pregnant women recall first-trimester NSAID use, particularly ibuprofen and aspirin, and such exposure is not a major risk factor for birth defects .
When taken in late pregnancy, however, indomethacin may cause constriction of the fetal ductus arteriosus and subsequent pulmonary hypertension.
Fetal ductal constriction is more likely with third trimester use that exceeds 72 hours.
The drug also may decrease fetal urine production and amnionic fluid volume (Rasanen, 1995; van der Heijden, 1994; Walker, 1994).
In one systematic review, indomethacin tocolysis was associated with a 1.5-fold risk for bronchopulmonary dysplasia, intraventricular hemorrhage, and necrotizing enterocolitis (Hammers, 2015a,b).
Based on a review of 35 cases of oligohydramnios or neonatal kidney problems reported to the FDA Adverse Event Reporting System database, the FDA recommends that pregnant women ≥20 weeks’ gestation avoid NSAID use .
If NSAIDs are needed for more than 48 hours, ultrasound evaluation of amnionic fluid should be considered.
Oligohydramnios usually resolves within 6 days of discontinuing NSAIDs, but there are cases in which infants have died of renal failure.
With aspirin, a low dosage of 100 mg daily or less does not confer a greater risk for constriction of the ductus arteriosus or for adverse infant outcomes .
As with other NSAIDs, however, high-dose aspirin use should be avoided, particularly in the third trimester.
Leflunomide This is a pyrimidine-synthesis inhibitor used to treat rheumatoid arthritis.
Leflunomide is considered contraindicated in pregnancy.
In rats and rabbits, leflunomide results in hydrocephalus, eye anomalies, skeletal anomalies, and embryo death when given at or below human-equivalent doses .
The active metabolite, teriflunomide, is detectable in plasma for up to 2 years following discontinuation of the medication.
Women who become pregnant while taking leflunomide, and even those of childbearing potential who have discontinued it, are recommended to undergo an accelerated drug elimination procedure with either cholestyramine or activated charcoal .
Reassuringly, studies of
exposed human pregnancies have not confirmed these teratogenic effects (Berard, 2018; Chambers, 2010).
In a cohort of 60 women with first-trimester leflunomide exposure who completed cholestyramine washout, the rate of birth defects was not increased .
A recent review of more than 500 exposed pregnancies found that the rate of major birth defects was 3 percent, similar to the general population .
The rate of spontaneous abortion also was not increased.
# Antimicrobial and Antiviral Drugs.
Medications used to treat infections are among those most frequently administered during pregnancy.
Over the years, experience has accrued regarding their general safety.
With few exceptions, commonly used antimicrobial agents are without embryo-fetal safety concerns.
Nitrofurantoin From NBDPS results, first-trimester nitrofurantoin exposure is linked to a twofold risk for cleft lip .
Considering that the birth prevalence of clefts approximates 1 case per 1000, the likelihood that a nitrofurantoinexposed fetus would not have a cleft would thus be 998 per 1000.
For other birth defects, initial associations with this antibiotic did not persist in the final NBDPS cohort .
In one systematic review of nitrofurantoin exposure in pregnancy, results of cohort and case-control studies differed .
Five cohort studies included 9275 exposed pregnancies and nearly 1.5 million unexposed pregnancies, and the review found no higher risk for any malformation.
However, among three case-control studies that had nearly 40,000 cases matched with 130,000 controls, the rate of hypoplastic left heart syndrome was threefold greater .
For context, this increase in risk would result in a birth prevalence of fewer than 1 case per 1000 exposed infants.
Nitrofurantoin is considered contraindicated in pregnant women with known or suspected glucose-6-phosphate dehydrogenase (G6PD) deficiency because of risk for hemolytic anemia and other hematologic abnormalities.
In the absence of G6PD deficiency, the There are no concerns with second- or third-trimester nitrofurantoin use, and first-trimester use is appropriate if no suitable alternatives are available.
Sulfonamides These drugs are often combined with trimethoprim and used to treat infections during pregnancy.
One indication is treatment of methicillinresistant Staphylococcus aureus (MRSA) infection.
The NBDPS, which included 107 pregnancies with periconceptional trimethoprimsulfamethoxazole exposure and birth defects, identified a fivefold greater risk to have offspring with esophageal atresia or diaphragmatic hernia .
Similar to findings with nitrofurantoin exposure, this degree of increase would confer a risk of approximately 1 case per 1000 exposed infants for these selected birth defects.
However, these findings have not been corroborated by other reports.
One review from the Medication Exposure in Pregnancy Risk Evaluation Program included more than 7500 infants with first-trimester exposure to trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole .
Compared with either unexposed infants or those exposed to penicillins or cephalosporins, no higher risk for any congenital abnormality was identified.
Given this reassuring data, we consider sulfonamides appropriate for first-trimester use if suitable alternatives are lacking.
Sulfonamides are considered contraindicated in pregnant women with known or suspected G6PD deficiency because of risk for hemolytic anemia and other hematologic abnormalities.
Additionally, sulfonamides displace bilirubin from protein-binding sites.
Thus, if given near the time of preterm delivery, these agents theoretically might worsen neonatal hyperbilirubinemia.
However, a population-based review of more than 800,000 births from Denmark found no association between exposure to sulfamethoxazole in late pregnancy and neonatal jaundice .
Tetracyclines These drugs are not commonly used in pregnant women.
They have been associated with yellowish-brown discoloration of the deciduous teeth when used after 25 weeks’ gestation.
The risk for subsequent dental caries is not increased (Billings, 2004; Kutscher, 1966).
Doxycycline has a reduced ability to chelate calcium orthophosphate compared with other tetracyclines and is preferred if needed.
A systematic review of doxycycline-exposed pregnancies identified no higher rates of either birth defects or staining of deciduous teeth .
Ribavirin This antiviral nucleoside analogue is a component of therapy for hepatitis C infection, discussed in Chapter 58 (p. 1038).
Ribavirin causes birth defects in multiple animal species at doses significantly lower than those recommended for human use.
Reported malformations include skull, palate, eye, skeleton, and gastrointestinal abnormalities.
The drug has a half-life of 12 days and persists in extravascular compartments following therapy discontinuation.
Treated women must use two forms of contraception and have monthly pregnancy tests while on therapy and for 6 months following drug discontinuation .
Ribavirin use is also contraindicated in men whose partners are pregnant.
# Antineoplastic Agents.
Cancer management in pregnancy includes many chemotherapeutic agents generally considered to be at least potentially toxic to the embryo, fetus, or both.
For the many novel polyclonal antibody therapies designated as antineoplastics, there is little information concerning safety.
The National Toxicology Program (2013) conducted a review of 300 pregnancies with first-trimester exposure and identified major malformations in 14 percent.
Treatment of cancer in pregnancy is discussed in Chapter 66 (p. 1163).
Risks associated with selected agents for which experience in pregnancy has accrued are considered next.
Cyclophosphamide This alkylating agent inflicts a chemical insult on developing fetal tissues and leads to cell death and heritable DNA alterations in surviving cells.
Pregnancy loss rates are greater, and reported fetal abnormalities include skeletal anomalies, limb defects, cleft palate, and eye abnormalities (Enns, 1999; Kirshon, 1988).
The risk for a major abnormality is estimated to be 18 percent .
Surviving infants may have growth abnormalities and developmental delays.
Environmental exposure among health-care workers is associated with a higher risk for spontaneous abortion.
Methotrexate This folic-acid antagonist is a potent teratogen.
It is used for cancer chemotherapy, immunosuppression of autoimmune diseases and psoriasis, nonsurgical treatment of ectopic pregnancy, and medical abortion.
It acts similarly to aminopterin, which is no longer used clinically, and can cause defects known collectively as the fetal methotrexate-aminopterin syndrome.
Associated craniofacial abnormalities include craniosynostosis with a “clover-leaf” skull, wide nasal bridge, low-set ears, and micrognathia .
Exposure has also been linked to central nervous system abnormalities, cardiac defects, and limb anomalies .
Intellectual impairment has been described.
The embryo is thought to be most vulnerable at 8 to 10 weeks postconception and at dosages of at least 10 mg/week.
However, this is not universally accepted .
Because of its distribution, methotrexate can remain in the body for prolonged periods.
Thus, preconceptional exposure is not without risk.
The standard 50-mg/m2 dose given to treat ectopic pregnancy or to induce abortion exceeds the 10-mg/week threshold dose.
Reports describe cardiac anomalies, particularly conotruncal defects, in intrauterine pregnancies inadvertently treated with methotrexate for suspected ectopic pregnancy (Dawson, 2014; Hyoun, 2012).
Tamoxifen This nonsteroidal selective estrogen-receptor modulator (SERM) is used as an adjuvant to treat breast cancer.
In animal studies, tamoxifen has been associated with malformations similar to those caused by diethylstilbestrol (DES) exposure in rodents, including vaginal adenosis.
One review of 167 pregnancies reported a fetal abnormality in 13 percent but emphasized that evidence was limited .
Abnormalities have included ambiguous genitalia and craniofacial anomalies.
Trastuzumab This is a recombinant monoclonal antibody directed to the human epidermal growth factor receptor 2 (HER2)
protein.
Used to treat breast and gastric cancers that express HER2 protein, this drug has not been associated with fetal malformations.
However, postmarketing surveillance identified cases of oligohydramnios sequence resulting in pulmonary hypoplasia, renal failure, skeletal abnormalities, and neonatal death .
Surveillance for these complications is recommended for exposed pregnancies and for those treated at any time in the 7 months prior to conception.
A trastuzumab pregnancy exposure registry and a pregnancy pharmacovigilance program have been established to monitor pregnancy outcomes.
These warnings also apply to those treated with ado-trastuzumab emtansine.
# Endothelin-receptor Antagonists.
Bosentan, ambrisentan, and macitentan are three endothelin-receptor antagonists used to treat pulmonary arterial hypertension .
The endothelin-receptor signaling pathway is important for neural-crest development.
Mice deficient in endothelin receptors develop neural-crest cell defects that include craniofacial and cardiac outflow tract abnormalities (de Raaf, 2015).
Each of these three agents has been found to cause similar birth defects in multiple animal species (Janssen, 2019a,b).
No human data are available.
Endothelin-receptor antagonists may be obtained only through restricted access programs, each of which has stringent requirements that include contraception and monthly pregnancy testing (Gilead, 2019; Janssen, 2019a,b).
# Immunosuppressant Medications.
Selected autoimmune diseases and their treatment are reviewed in Chapter 62 (p. 1109).
Corticosteroids Glucocorticoids and mineralocorticoids have antiinflammatory and immunosuppressive actions.
They are used to treat serious disorders such as asthma and autoimmune disease.
Corticosteroids have been associated with orofacial clefts in animal studies, but the absolute risk is small.
In a metaanalysis of case-control studies by the Motherisk Program, systemic corticosteroid exposure was associated with a threefold rate increase, conferring an absolute risk of 3 clefts per 1000 exposed fetuses .
A 10-year prospective cohort study by the same group, however, did not identify an increased overall risk for major malformations.
Based on these findings, corticosteroids are not considered to represent a major teratogenic risk.
Potential risks associated with prednisone or methylprednisolone are considered to be lower than those with other corticosteroids.
Prednisolone, the active metabolite of prednisone, is itself metabolized and rendered inactive by the placental enzyme 11β-hydroxysteroid dehydrogenase 2 .
Thus, it is thought to reach the fetus less effectively.
Mycophenolate Mofetil This inosine monophosphate dehydrogenase inhibitor, and a related agent, mycophenolic acid, are immunosuppressants.
They are used to prevent rejection in organ-transplant recipients and to treat autoimmune disease .
Mycophenolate is a potent teratogen.
From the National Transplantation Pregnancy Registry, of pregnancies in which mycophenolate was not discontinued until after the first trimester, birth defects complicated 30 percent, and another 30 percent spontaneously aborted .
One prospective review by the European Network of Teratology Information Services similarly identified a spontaneous loss rate of nearly 30 percent in exposed pregnancies.
More than 20 percent of liveborn infants had major anomalies .
Many affected infants have a pattern of defects termed mycophenolate embryopathy.
This includes microtia, auditory canal atresia, clefts, coloboma and other eye anomalies, short fingers with hypoplastic nails, and cardiac defects (Anderka, 2009; Merlob, 2009).
A Risk Evaluation and Mitigation Strategy (REMS) has been developed for mycophenolate prescribers who treat women with reproductive potential.
REMS are safety strategies mandated by the FDA to help manage known risks associated with a medicine yet still allow patients to have access to the benefits of a given drug.
# Lead.
Lead crosses the placenta via passive diffusion.
Prenatal lead exposure is associated with fetal-growth
impairment and with childhood neurodevelopmental delays.
According to the CDC (2010), no level of lead exposure is considered safe in pregnancy.
Although routine testing is not recommended, risk factors should be assessed in all pregnancies .
Care and testing for atrisk pregnancies is discussed in Chapter 10 (p. 188).
# Mercury.
The developing nervous system is particularly susceptible to mercury.
In the 1950s and early 1960s, children born near Minamata Bay, Japan were found to have congenital Minamata disease—severe neurological abnormalities from methylmercury exposure in utero .
Prenatal exposure causes disturbances in neuronal cell division and migration.
This leads to a range of defects from microcephaly to intellectual disability, choreo-athetoid movement abnormalities, motor delays, and behavioral abnormalities .
The principal concern for prenatal mercury exposure is the consumption of certain species of large fish and seafood .
Methylmercury cannot be eliminated by cooking.
It crosses the placenta and can accumulate in the fetus.
The FDA (2019) advises that pregnant women and breastfeeding mothers avoid consumption of king mackerel, marlin, orange roughy, shark, swordfish, tilefish, and bigeye tuna.
# Psychiatric Medications.
Treatment of psychiatric illness in pregnancy, including a discussion of the risks and benefits of various psychiatric medications, is described in Chapter 64 (p. 1142).
Antipsychotic Medications No antipsychotic medications are considered teratogenic.
Exposed neonates can manifest abnormal extrapyramidal muscle movements and withdrawal symptoms that include agitation, abnormally enhanced or diminished muscle tone, tremor, agitation, somnolence, respiratory abnormalities, and feeding difficulty.
Such findings are nonspecific and transient.
An FDA (2017) alert cited all medications in this class.
Included are older medications like haloperidol and chlorpromazine and newer medications such as aripiprazole, olanzapine, quetiapine, and risperidone.
Lithium This medication has been associated with Ebstein anomaly, a rare cardiac abnormality that otherwise complicates only 1 per 20,000 births.
Ebstein anomaly is characterized by apical displacement of the tricuspid valve, often resulting in severe tricuspid regurgitation and marked right atrial enlargement.
A report from the Lithium Baby Registry initially suggested that the risk for Ebstein anomaly was as high as 3 percent.
However, subsequent series have identified an attributable risk for Ebstein anomaly and cooccurring right-sided cardiac anomalies of only 1 to 4 cases per 1000 exposed pregnancies (Patorno, 2017; Yacobi, 2008).
The NBDPS found that just 1 of 135 cases of Ebstein anomaly occurred in the setting of lithium exposure .
Neonatal lithium toxicity stems from exposure near delivery.
The manufacturer recommends that if possible, the dosage should be decreased or drug discontinued 2 to 3 days prior to delivery to reduce this risk .
Findings may persist for up to 2 weeks and may include cardiac arrhythmias, hypoglycemia, nephrogenic diabetes insipidus, and a “floppy infant syndrome” .
The latter may include hypotonia, respiratory distress or apnea, bradycardia, cyanosis, and feeding difficulties .
Selective Serotonin- and Norepinephrine-reuptake Inhibitors These medications have been studied more than almost any other, apart from Bendectin (p. 146).
As a class, they are not considered major teratogens .
The one exception is paroxetine, which has been associated with a slightly higher risk for cardiac anomalies, particularly atrial and ventricular septal defects.
Metaanalyses have identified a pooled odds ratio of just 1.3 for paroxetine and cardiac abnormalities (Berard, 2016; Wurst, 2010).
However, a review of nearly 1 million pregnancies from the nationwide Medicaid Analytic eXtract identified no significant association between paroxetine use in the first trimester and fetal cardiac abnormalities .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019f) recommends that women planning pregnancy avoid paroxetine.
Fetal
echocardiography should be considered for those with first-trimester paroxetine exposure.
Neonatal effects have been associated with prenatal exposure to selective serotonin-reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) and selective norepinephrine-reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs).
Approximately 25 percent of neonates exposed to SSRIs in late pregnancy manifest one or more nonspecific findings considered to represent poor neonatal adaptation (Costei, 2002; Jordan, 2008).
Collectively termed the neonatal behavioral syndrome, findings can include jitteriness, irritability, hyper- or hypotonia, feeding abnormalities, vomiting, hypoglycemia, thermoregulatory instability, and respiratory abnormalities.
Fortunately, these neonatal behaviors are typically mild and self-limited and last approximately 2 days.
Jordan and coworkers (2008) reported that affected newborns were not more likely to require a higher level of care, to experience respiratory abnormalities, or to have prolonged hospitalization.
Rarely, neonates exposed to SSRIs in late pregnancy have demonstrated more severe adaptation abnormalities .
Another concern with late-pregnancy exposure is the possible association of SSRI medications with persistent pulmonary hypertension of the newborn (PPHN).
The baseline incidence approximates 2 cases per 1000 term newborns.
PPHN is characterized by elevated pulmonary vascular resistance with right-to-left shunting and resultant hypoxemia.
Two population-based cohort studies—together involving more than 5 million pregnancies—identified an attributable risk of only 1 to 2 cases per 1000 births (Huybrechts, 2015; Kieler, 2012).
Moreover, cases of PPHN associated with SSRI medication have not been severe .
# Retinoids.
Vitamin A derivatives are among the most potent human teratogens.
By inhibiting neural-crest cell migration during embryogenesis, they create a pattern of cranial neural-crest defects—termed retinoic acid embryopathy— that involve the CNS, face, heart, and thymus .
Specific anomalies may include ventriculomegaly, maldevelopment of the facial bones or cranium, microtia or anotia, micrognathia, cleft palate, conotruncal heart defects, and thymic aplasia or hypoplasia.
Figure 8-3.
Retinoic acid embryopathy.
A. Bilateral microtia or anotia with stenosis of external ear canal.
B. Flat, depressed nasal bridge and ocular hypertelorism.
Reproduced with permission from permission from Dr. Edward Lammer.
Acitretin This retinoid is used to treat severe psoriasis.
It was introduced to replace etretinate, a lipophilic retinoid with such a long half-life (120 days) that birth defects resulted more than 2 years after therapy was discontinued.
Although acitretin has a short half-life, it is metabolized to etretinate, and thus remains in the body for prolonged periods .
To obviate exposure, the manufacturer of acitretin has developed a pregnancy risk management program.
Called “Do Your P.A.R.T”—pregnancy prevention actively required during and after treatment, this program promotes a delay of conception for at least 3 years following therapy discontinuation.
Bexarotene This retinoid is used to treat refractory cutaneous T-cell lymphoma.
When given to rats in doses comparable to those for human therapy, fetuses developed eye and ear abnormalities, cleft palate, and incomplete ossification.
For a woman to receive bexarotene, the manufacturer requires two forms of contraception that are initiated 1 month before therapy and continued for 1 month after it is discontinued.
This is coupled with monthly pregnancy testing during treatment .
Males who have partners who could become pregnant are advised to use condoms during sexual intercourse while taking bexarotene and for 1 month after discontinuing therapy.
Isotretinoin 13-cis-Retinoic acid is a vitamin A isomer that stimulates epithelial cell differentiation.
It is primarily used to treat recalcitrant nodular acne.
Firsttrimester exposure is associated with a high rate of pregnancy loss, and up to a third of infants have malformations .
The iPLEDGE program is an FDA-mandated REMS for
isotretinoin and is found at www.ipledgeprogram.com.
This web-based, restricted-distribution program requires participation for all patients, physicians, and pharmacies to help eliminate embryo–fetal exposure.
Other countries have instituted similar programs, however, inadvertent exposure remains a global concern (AutretLeca, 2010; Crijns, 2011).
Topical Retinoids These compounds, initially used to treat acne, have become so popular for sun-damage treatment that they are called cosmeceuticals .
The most commonly used topical agents are tretinoin, isotretinoin, and adapalene.
Systemic absorption is low, and this argues against plausible teratogenicity.
Isolated case reports have described malformations following topical tretinoin, and it is unknown whether this is due to variability in absorption or perhaps potential individual susceptibility .
A prospective study by the European Network of Teratology Information Services found no higher rates of birth defects or spontaneous losses, and no case of retinoid embryopathy .
A systematic review of 635 pregnancies exposed to topical retinoids identified no higher risk for congenital malformations, spontaneous abortion, stillbirth, low birthweight, or preterm delivery .
Notably, the manufacturer of tazarotene cautions that application over a sufficient body surface area could be comparable to oral treatment.
Accordingly, its use in pregnancy is not recommended .
Vitamin A There are two natural forms of vitamin A.
First, provitamin A carotenoids, which include beta-carotene, alpha-carotene, and beta-cryptoxanthin, are precursors found in fruits and vegetables.
The body converts carotenoids into vitamin A.
They have never been shown to cause birth defects .
Second, preformed vitamin A, also called retinol, has been associated with cranial neural-crest defects when more than 10,000 IU per day is consumed in the first trimester .
Preformed vitamin A is present in liver, fish oils, milk, eggs, and in vitamin pills and dietary supplements.
It seems reasonable to avoid doses of preformed preparations that exceed the recommended 3000 IU daily allowance .
# Sex Hormones.
Selected functions and effects of male and female hormones on the developing fetus are reviewed in Chapter 3 (p. 31).
Androgen exposure may cause varying degrees of virilization in female fetuses and may result in ambiguous genitalia (Fig. 3-3, p. 34).
# Thalidomide and Analogues.
Possibly the most notorious human teratogen, thalidomide causes malformations in 20 percent of fetuses exposed between 34 and 50 days menstrual age.
The characteristic malformation is phocomelia—an absence or underdevelopment of one or more long bones.
As a result, hands or feet may attach to the trunk, occasionally by a small rudimentary bone.
Cardiac defects, gastrointestinal abnormalities, external ear and eye malformations, and other limb-reduction defects also are common following thalidomide exposure.
The manufacturer reports that up to 40 percent of affected newborns do not survive the neonatal period .
Thalidomide was marketed outside the United States from 1956 to 1960, before its teratogenicity was appreciated.
The ensuing disaster, with thousands of affected children, was instructive of several important teratological principles.
First, the placenta is not an effective barrier to the transfer of toxic substances from mother to embryo .
Second, different species manifest considerable variability in their susceptibility to drugs and chemicals.
Namely, thalidomide produced no defects in multiple rodent species and was assumed to be safe for humans.
Last, timing of exposure may be closely related to the type of defect .
For example, upper-limb amelia may develop with thalidomide exposure during days 24 to 30 postconception, upper-limb phocomelia with exposure during days 24 to 33, and lower-limb phocomelia with exposure during days 27 to 33.
Thalidomide was first approved in the United States in 1999 and currently is used to treat erythema leprosum nodosum and multiple myeloma .
The FDA has mandated a web-based,
restricteddistribution program for thalidomide, called THALOMID REMS, which is required before patients, physicians, and pharmacies can access the medication.
Lenalidomide and pomalidomide are analogues of thalidomide.
Both cross the placenta in animal species.
Lenalidomide is used to treat some types of myelodysplastic syndrome and multiple myeloma.
It has been found to cause thalidomide-like limb abnormalities in monkeys .
Pomalidomide is used to treat refractory multiple myeloma and acquired immunodeficiency syndrome (AIDS)-related Kaposi sarcoma.
It is teratogenic in rats and rabbits .
Restricted-distribution programs similar to those used for thalidomide have been developed for these analogues.
# Thyroid Medications.
Methimazole This thionamide drug is used to treat hyperthyroidism.
Methimazole has been associated with a 2-fold increased risk for aplasia cutis congenita, as well as choanal atresia and esophageal atresia .
This constellation of findings has been termed methimazole embryopathy.
Aplasia cutis is a rare abnormality characterized by a full-thickness skin defect, usually the scalp, occasionally with a defect of underlying bone.
In a study of more than 1000 methimazole-treated pregnancies, Yoshihara and colleagues (2015) identified the embryopathy in 1 to 2 percent.
Treatment of hyperthyroidism in pregnancy is reviewed in Chapter 61.
Radioiodine Radioactive iodine-131 is used for treatment of thyroid cancer and thyrotoxicosis and for diagnostic thyroid scanning.
It is also a component of iodine-131 tositumomab therapy, which is employed to treat a type of nonHodgkin lymphoma.
Radioiodine is contraindicated during pregnancy because it readily crosses the placenta and is concentrated in the fetal thyroid gland by 12 weeks’ gestation.
It may cause severe or irreversible fetal and neonatal hypothyroidism, which can lead to decreased mental capacity and delayed skeletal maturation.
Pregnancy testing should be performed before administration of radioiodine-131, and it is recommended that pregnancy be avoided for 6 to 12 months following treatment .
A review of more than 3000 pregnancies in which women delayed conception for at least 6 months after receiving radioactive iodine treatment identified no increase in pregnancy losses or congenital malformations .
Concerns for the breastfeeding mother stem from breast exposure to the radioisotope.
# Warfarin.
This anticoagulant is a vitamin K antagonist with a long half-life.
Because of its low molecular weight, it readily crosses the placenta and may cause embryotoxic and fetotoxic effects.
It is considered contraindicated in pregnancy with one important exception.
As discussed in Chapter 52 (p. 922), warfarin is used to treat women with mechanical heart valves who are at high risk for thromboembolism .
Warfarin embryopathy is characterized by stippled epiphyses and nasal hypoplasia .
In one review of 63 cases attributed to warfarin exposure, 80 percent displayed characteristic findings, which include depressed nasal bridge with nasal hypoplasia and choanal atresia, along with stippled epiphyses of the femur, humerus, calcanei, and distal phalanges .
The embryopathy may result from exposure between 6 and 9 weeks’ gestation .
Prevalence following exposure during this critical period is estimated to be 6 percent.
One metaanalysis of cases in which the warfarin dosage was ≤5 mg/d identified embryopathy in 1 percent of exposed fetuses.
This suggests that risk may be dose dependent .
Figure 8-4.
Warfarin embryopathy or fetal warfarin syndrome: nasal hypoplasia and depressed nasal bridge seen in a fetal sonographic image (A) and in the same newborn (B).
If used beyond the first trimester, warfarin may lead to hemorrhage into fetal structures, which can cause abnormal growth and deformation from scarring .
Nearly 50 percent of reported embryopathy cases also have CNS anomalies (van Driel, 2002).
Abnormalities can include agenesis of the corpus callosum; cerebellar vermian agenesis, which is the Dandy-Walker malformation; microphthalmia; and optic atrophy.
Affected
infants are also at risk for blindness, deafness, and developmental delays.
# Tobacco.
Cigarette smoking is the leading preventable cause of perinatal mortality.
At least 7 percent of women report smoking cigarettes during pregnancy .
Cigarette smoke contains a complex mixture of nicotine, cotinine, cyanide, thiocyanate, carbon monoxide, cadmium, lead, and various hydrocarbons .
In addition to being fetotoxic, many of these substances have vasoactive effects or reduce oxygen levels.
Although tobacco is not considered a major human teratogen, selected birth defects have been reported to occur with greater frequency following exposure.
Cigarette smoking and exposure to second-hand smoke have been associated with up to a 1.5-fold risk for orofacial clefts (Kummet, 2016; Sabbagh, 2015).
This equates to an attributable risk of approximately 1 case per 2000 births.
It is plausible that the vasoactive properties of tobacco smoke could produce congenital defects related to vascular disturbances.
For example, the prevalence of Poland sequence, which is caused by an interruption in the vascular supply to one side of the fetal chest and ipsilateral arm, has been reported to occur two times more commonly among cigarette smokers .
The NBDPS similarly found an association between active or passive cigarette smoking and limb reduction defects, and an overall increase in risk of 25 percent .
A small increased risk for fetal cardiac anomalies also has been reported and may be dose related (Alverson, 2011; Malik, 2008; Sullivan, 2015).
The most prevalent obstetrical complication from smoking is a dosedependent reduction in fetal growth.
Newborns of mothers who smoke weigh on average 200 g less than newborns of nonsmokers (D’Souza, 1981).
Smoking doubles the risk of low birthweight and raises the risk of fetalgrowth restriction two- to threefold .
As such, cigarette smoking accounts for 15 percent of low-birthweight neonates .
Even secondhand smoke increases the risk for low birthweight.
Other adverse pregnancy outcomes associated with cigarette smoking include preterm birth, prelabor rupture of membranes, placenta previa, and placenta abruption .
Approximately one third of cases of sudden infant death syndrome have been attributed to cigarette smoking (Anderson, 2019; Dietz, 2010).
Risks of childhood asthma and obesity also are increased.
When inquiring about tobacco use, providers should include alternative nicotine delivery products.
All forms of nicotine cross the placenta.
None is considered safe in pregnancy.
Vaping or e-cigarette products heat an “eliquid” containing nicotine—and often additional contaminants—along with a flavoring agent.
Nicotine is associated with adverse effects on fetal brain and lung development (American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists, 2020b; Spindel, 2016).
In adults, vaping has been linked to serious lung injury known as EVALI—e-cigarette or vaping-associated lung injury .
Animal studies of hookah use, in which tobacco smoke is filtered through a water bowl, demonstrate lower birthweight and increased markers of cardiac stress .
Smoking cessation should be strongly encouraged.
Counseling includes avoidance of secondhand smoke and all nicotine-replacement products, such as patches, gum, and lozenges.
A hotline is available from the Centers of Disease Control and Prevention and can be accessed by calling 1-800-QUITNOW.
The U.S. Preventive Services Task Force has recommended that behavioral interventions be offered at the initial visit and continued throughout pregnancy .
# Herbal Medicinal Products.
In large survey studies from North America and Europe, 30 to 60 percent of women report using herbal remedies during pregnancy (Kennedy, 2016; Pallivalapila, 2015).
These products are not regulated by the FDA, and there is a paucity of controlled studies assessing their safety and efficacy.
The identity, quantity, and purity of each ingredient are usually unknown.
Authors of a recent systematic review that included more than 1 million pregnancies concluded that in the absence of more
safety data, the use of herbal medicinal products in pregnancy should be discouraged .
Selected herbal remedies and their reported adverse effects are shown in Table 8-5.
TABLE 8-5.
Pharmacological Actions and Adverse Effects of Some Herbal Medicines # Drugs of Abuse.
Substance abuse is not uncommon in pregnancy.
Assessment of outcomes attributable to illicit drug use is often confounded by factors such as poor maternal health, malnutrition, and infectious disease.
Polysubstance abuse further complicates assessment of outcomes associated with any one drug.
Moreover, illegal substances may contain toxic contaminants such as lead, cyanide, herbicides, and pesticides.
Impurities added as diluents may independently have serious adverse perinatal effects.
As noted on page 149, alcohol is a significant teratogen.
Because it is legally obtained and ubiquitous, its use confounds the study of illicit drug teratogenicity.
Similarly, tobacco use confounds the effect of drugs on fetal growth.
Cocaine With this CNS stimulant, most adverse outcomes result from its vasoconstrictive and hypertensive effects.
Serious potential maternal complications are cerebrovascular hemorrhage, myocardial damage, and placental abruption.
Studies of congenital abnormalities and cocaine exposure have yielded conflicting results, but associations with cleft palate, cardiovascular abnormalities, and urinary tract anomalies have been reported (Chasnoff, 1988; Lipshultz, 1991; van Gelder, 2009).
Cocaine use is also associated with fetal-growth restriction and preterm delivery.
Children exposed as fetuses have risks for behavioral abnormalities and cognitive impairments (Bada, 2011; Gouin, 2011).
Marijuana This is the recreational drug most commonly used in pregnancy .
Based on data from the National Survey on Drug Use and Health, nearly 4 percent of pregnant women reported using marijuana in 2014 .
Among women diagnosed with nausea and vomiting of pregnancy, the prevalence of marijuana use increased from 7 to 11 percent from 2009 to 2016 .
Of concern is that the increase in prevalence is related to perceived safety and efficacy.
In a study of 400 cannabis dispensaries, nearly 70 percent advised a caller posing as a pregnant woman with nausea at 8 weeks’ gestation to use marijuana .
However, no data support efficacy of marijuana for nausea and vomiting of pregnancy, and there are indeed safety concerns .
Cannabinoids are not considered to be major teratogens, but they cross the placenta, and endogenous cannabinoids play key roles in brain development.
In animals, cannabinoids are involved in neuronal proliferation, migration, and differentiation .
Adverse developmental outcomes reported in exposed children include decreased attention span and lower scores on tests of visual problem solving and visual-motor coordination (Fried, 2003; Willford 2010).
Pregnancy outcome data are somewhat limited by the confounding risks of concomitant tobacco use.
In one metaanalysis of nearly 8000 exposed pregnancies, only those with concomitant tobacco use had increased rates of preterm birth and low-birthweight neonates .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019b) has stated that the effects of marijuana may be as serious as those of cigarette smoking or alcohol consumption.
Because of neurodevelopmental concerns, women who are pregnant or contemplating pregnancy should avoid marijuana use.
Methamphetamine This sympathomimetic amine is derived from dextroamphetamine.
It enhances dopamine release and blocks its reuptake.
Methamphetamine is prescribed to treat attention deficit hyperactivity disorder and narcolepsy.
Abuse has been rising in the United States since the late 1980s .
Methamphetamine is not considered teratogenic.
However, use in pregnancy is consistently associated with small-for-gestational age newborns, and children are at risk for developmental delays and behavioral abnormalities (Derauf, 2012; Eze, 2016; Gabrhelik, 2021; O’Connor, 2020).
Behavioral abnormalities have been described in both infants and school-aged children .
Hypertensive complications, placental abruption, preterm birth, and stillbirth are other associated adverse outcomes .
Opioids The dramatic rise in narcotic use among nonpregnant and pregnant individuals has been aptly termed an epidemic.
Opioids are not major teratogens.
However, the NBDPS did identify a slightly greater risk for spina bifida, gastroschisis, and cardiac abnormalities with periconceptional opioid exposure .
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019d) stresses that this potential, small increase in birth defects with maintenance therapy should be weighed against the risks associated with uncontrolled opioid abuse.
Heroin addiction is associated with adverse pregnancy outcomes from the effects of repeated narcotic withdrawal on the fetus and placenta.
These include preterm birth, placental abruption, fetal-growth restriction, and fetal death.
Neonatal narcotic withdrawal, called the neonatal abstinence syndrome, may manifest in 40 to 90 percent of exposed newborns (Blinick, 1973; Creanga, 2012; Dashe, 2002; Zelson, 1973).
As discussed in Chapter 33 (p. 605), CNS irritability may progress to seizures if untreated and may be accompanied by tachypnea, apneic episodes, poor feeding, and failure to thrive.
At-risk neonates are closely monitored using a scoring system, and those severely affected are treated with opioids .
The proportion of exposed newborns developing neonatal abstinence syndrome has risen significantly in recent years (Creanga, 2012; Lind, 2015).
The American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists (2019d) recommends that pregnant women with opioid-use disorder be maintained on opioid-agonist therapy to reduce the risks associated with illicit opioid abuse and associated behaviors.
Treatment includes either buprenorphine, which may be given in an office-based setting by a licensed buprenorphine prescriber, or methadone, usually through a licensed outpatient opioid treatment program.
A multidisciplinary treatment program is recommended to reduce the likelihood of additional opioid abuse while on maintenance therapy.
Withdrawal from methadone during pregnancy is discouraged because of high relapse rates .
At Parkland Hospital, pregnant opioid users who decline maintenance therapy are offered inpatient hospitalization for controlled methadone taper.
The goal is to reduce the likelihood of neonatal abstinence syndrome (Dashe, 2002; Stewart, 2013).
Miscellaneous Drugs Phencyclidine (PCP) or angel dust is not associated with congenital anomalies.
More than half of exposed newborns, however, experience withdrawal symptoms characterized by tremors, jitteriness, and irritability.
Toluene is a common solvent used in paints and glue.
Occupational exposure is reported to have significant fetal risks .
When abused by women in early pregnancy, it is associated with toluene embryopathy, which is phenotypically similar to fetal alcohol syndrome.
Abnormalities include pre- and postnatal growth deficiency, microcephaly, midface hypoplasia, short palpebral fissures, and wide nasal bridge .
Up to 40 percent of exposed children have developmental delays .